ARIEL LUBONJA

@ ariel@cs.jhu.edu

https://ariellubonja.github.io/

∂ https://www.linkedin.com/in/ariel-lubonja-235a6b197/
☆ https://medium.com/@lubonjaariel

PROJECTS

NLP - Chatbot for the University of Southern California (USC) - Alice in Wonderland

University of Southern California **=** 05/2019 - 07/2020 https://alice.wonderland.usc.edu/chat/alice-endpoint.html

- Natural Language Processing (NLP). Researched Kaldi, Rasa, Mycroft, and early AWS solutions, picovoice, CMU pronouncing dictionary.
- 1. Mycroft.ai Skill Add Skill to the existing Mycroft.ai chatbot. Lack of clear documentation hindered this effort.
- 2. Google's BERT. Fine-tuned BERT on 600 Q&A pairs about Alice. Deployed on a AWS machine + GPU. Inference took 50 seconds on CPU, 13sec on GPU - too slow - Goal: <6 seconds inference
- 3. Google Dialogflow, featuring a model based on BERT, a user-friendly UI, ability to label positive and negative examples and with backgroundmanaged training
- Implemented Mycroft as a Speech-to-Text engine for transcribing user's speech
- See Full-Stack Developer section for non-Machine Learning development & deployment effort

Dall-E Al Image Generation Extension for Google Docs, Sheets, Slides

https://workspace.google.com/marketplace/app/ai_generated_images_dalle/8670 97413141?hl=en&pann=docs_addon_widget

- Built a Google Workspace app to serve Dall-E generated images to Google Docs, Sheets and Slides documents
- >5000 downloads, 4-star average rating

Kaggle: Stable Diffusion - Image to Prompts

- https://www.kaggle.com/competitions/stable-diffusion-image-to-prompts? utm_medium=email&utm_source=gamma&utm_campaign=comp-stable-diffusion-
- Can you recover the prompt that produced a specfic image output from Stable Diffusion? Competition in progress...

Master Thesis: Parallel Implementation of Graph **Encoder Embedding in Ligra**

= 01/2022 - 05/2022

https://github.com/Ariel5/GraphEmd

Graph Embedding is a popular method in graph machine learning for forming embeddings that allow for easy comparison of nodes

- Built a highly scalable version of Graph Encoder Embedding using the Ligra graph-parallel framework
- 1400x speedup over the original in Ligra
- Implemented a Python-Numba approach for ease of use. Achieves 289x speedup

WORK EXPERIENCE

Full Stack Developer -Python/Django, JavaEE, Angular

=== 11/2018 - 08/2021

Sofia, Bulgaria

jBoxers is a company that offers software solutions in the fields of Al, Microservices, DevOps and Cloud

- Chatbot for the University of Southern California with Dr. Laura Toloși, using Mycroft as a Speech-to-Text and Google Dialogflow as language models (see Projects). Flask API
- Developed the Desktop app for Alice. By using Electron, I cut down the app development time to 3 weeks instead of multiple months
- JavaEE WebSockets for non-REST chatting
- AWS & Google Cloud deployment + CI/CD, Docker, Vagrant, Datalku
- Other Duties: Use Case discussion and design with Library of Congress (LoC) project owner
- Developed enterprise solutions for LoC Virtual Card Catalog and Braille
- Supervised 2 summer interns

Junior Developer - JavaEE, Angular, Python/Django, SQL

= 05/2017 - 11/2018

- Ongoing project for LoC, using Angular for frontend and JavaEE/Spring for backend
- Developed tests using Sonar, JUnit, Selenium and Protractor

ACHIEVEMENTS



Fellowship to Johns Hopkins University

1/14 students funded by the Government of Albania, in their Excellence Scholarship, for students admitted to top-15 universities



Full Scholarship to American University in Bulgaria

1/11 students awarded by the America-Albania Development Fund



334/340 in the GRE exam

93rd percentile in Quantitative (168/170) 97th percentile in Verbal Comp. (166/170)

PASSIONS



Skiing, Weightlifting, Running



Cars, Scalable Algorithms

EDUCATION

Doctor of Philosophy, Computer Science

Johns Hopkins University

05/2022 - Present

GPA 3.93 / 4.0

- Graph Learning & Embedding Graph Neural Networks, node embedding, edge prediction, transductive learning with **Graph Attention Networks**. Thorough knowledge of node2vec and Graph Encoder Embedding. Extensive work on scaling these algorithms
- Work on scaling <u>Leiden</u> community-detection graph algorithm
- Maintaining the Johns Hopkins Turbulence Database
- Computer Vision: Transforms, dictionaries & filters, Convolutions, CNNs, segmentation, Edge & boundary detection, sparsity
- Given multiple presentations at various audience levels. Effective at presentations and communicating complex ideas.

Master of Science in Engineering - Data Science

GPA 3.72 / 4.0

Johns Hopkins University

= 01/2021 - 05/2022 Paltimore, Maryland, USA

- Scaling up algorithms Parallel Programming, MapReduce/Hadoop, Spark, Dask, Ray, GPU/TPUs, Multithreading, Memory Hierarchy, OpenMP
- Machine Learning & Deep Learning: Regression, CNNs, Decision Trees, Random Forests, SVMs, RNN, LSTM, Transformers, Markov Models. Significant experience w/ PyTorch
- Algorithms & Data Structures: complexity theory, big-O, sorting, advanced data structures, dynamic programming, graph algorithms, Linear prog.
- Mathematical Statistics Model fitting, estimators, bias-variance tradeoff, convergence, ANOVA, hypothesis testing, Regression
- Optimization Stochastic Gradient Descent, line/grid-search, Newton's Method, BFGS, Trust Region Methods, convex, (non-)smooth opti.
- Signal Processing finding sparsest solution to underdetermined systems. L1 (Lasso) and L0 (Matching Pursuit) techniques. Applications in facial recognition and image processing

Bachelor in Computer Science

GPA 3.57 / 4.0

American University in Bulgaria

m 09/2014 - 05/2018

SKILLS

Python PyTorch

Sequence Models Transformers

Mycroft

Scikit-learn

OpenMP

SQL

AI/ML

Graph Neural Networks

Convolutional Neural Networks

Linear/Logistic Regression

XGBoost

AWS

C++

Google Dialogflow

Google Apps Script

Docker